Guide to the Horace Bushnell Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Horace Bushnell Papers
1832-1902
RG 39
Yale University Divinity School Library
2
(5 boxes)
The collection includes five diaries containing valuable biographical information and documenting Bushnell's trip abroad, 1845-1846, and manuscript sermons, 1832-1875, which give insight into the less formal aspects of Bushnell's thought. The material written about Bushnell during his lifetime pertains to the controversy associated with his theological beliefs. Horace Bushnell was born in Bantam, Connecticut on April 14, 1802. He was educated at Yale (B.A., 1827; M.A., 1830; B.D., 1833), and received degrees from Wesleyan University, Harvard, and Yale. He served as pastor of North Church, Hartford, CT from 1833-1859. He was the author of God in Christ (1849) and Christ in Theology (1851), as well as other works uncongenial to the orthodox theology of his times.
Bushnell, Horace, 1802-1876
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Howell Cheney, 1945.
Biographical / Historical
1802 Apr 14 Born in Bantam, CT
1827 B.A., Yale
1829-1831 Tutor in Yale College
1830 M.A., Yale
1833 B.D., Yale
1833 Ordained pastor of the North Church, Hartford, CT
1842 D.D., Wesleyan University
1845-1846 Year spent abroad in Europe
1849 Published God in Christ, a work uncongenial to the orthodoxy of the times. Conservative ministers in Connecticut sought to bring Bushnell to trial for heresy.
1851 Published, Christ in Theology, which answered his critics.
1852 S.T.D., Harvard
1856 Traveled to California for health reasons, became interested in the problems of developing the region.
1859 Retired from the ministry for health reasons but continued to write and publish.
1871 L.L.D., Yale
1876Feb 17 Died
Biographical information taken from: Historical Register of Yale University, 1701-1937 and Dictionary of American Biography
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence, 1848, n.d.
II. Diaries, 1845-1846.
III. Writings of Bushnell, 1832-1875.
IV. Material written about Bushnell, 1843-1902, n.d.
V. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1849-1902, n.d.
The correspondence section consists of two letters written and signed by Bushnell, their recipients unidentified.
The diaries of Series II are a five volume record of Bushnell's impressions during his trip abroad in 1845-1846. These journals would be of greatest value for biographical research. Excerpts from them have been published in Bushnell's daughter's book, Life and Letters of Horace Bushnell.
The writings of Bushnell are divided into three sections:
A. Manuscript sermons and discourses (1832-1875, n.d.)
B. Published sermons and discourses (1839-1959, n.d.)
C. Miscellaneous (1839-1873, n.d.)
The manuscript sermons give valuable insight into the less formal aspects of Bushnell's thought. Some of these sermons have been published in whole or in part, largely in Bushnell's posthumous volume, The Spirit in Man. Although many of them were not considered sufficiently valuable or well organized to be included in his published works as entire sermons, these unpublished writings contain material that can assist in tracing the development of his thought. In many cases the unpublished portions of the sermons contain statements of doctrine that were apparently omitted as not being of interest to the general reader.
The published sermons and discourses are largely duplicates of ones already cataloged in the Library's collection, and are included with Bushnell's papers to provide consolidated access. The miscellaneous writings of Bushnell included newspaper articles, a prayer for a wedding, and explanations of two patents obtained by him.
The material written about Bushnell during his lifetime pertains to the controversy associated with his theological beliefs. Bushnell's opposition to the rigid rationalism of his times and his attempts to redefine Christianity in terms of human experience were the cause of much accusation and debate. Additional material in this section stems from the centenary celebration of Bushnell's birth in 1902. Series V includes a letter from Amos Cheseborough to T.T. Munger, biographer of Bushnell, that traces Bushnell's genealogical descent.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1848, n.d.
II. Diaries, 1845-1846
III. Writings of Bushnell, 1832-1875
IV. Material written about Bushnell, 1843-1902, n.d.
V. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1849-1902, n.d.
Church work; Congregational churches -- United States; Theology; Diaries; Sermons; Authors; Clergy; Theologians; Bushnell, Horace, 1802-1876
- Correspondence, Series I
  - To: "George", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - To: "Dear Sir", 1848 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Diaries, 1845 Jul 11-1845 Oct 11; Series II
  - Diary of trip abroad: Volume I, 1845 Jul 11-1845 Oct 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Volume II, 1845 Oct 12-1845 Nov 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Volume III, 1845 Nov 25-1845 Dec 19 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Volume IV, 1845 Dec 20-1846 Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Volume V, 1846 Feb 19-1846 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Writings of Bushnell, Series III
  - Manuscript Sermons and Discourses
    - Christ the Form of the Soul, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Church Catalogue of Rome II, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Corinthians 3:8, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Course of the World, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Death Abolished, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Death a Leveller of Distinctions, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - The Doctrine of Prayer, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - The Eternity of Love, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - The Everlasting Gospel (incomplete), 1847 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Existence Consummated in a State of Praise, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Giving Account Each One to God, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - God' Meaning in Probation, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Gods One Family, 1857 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - God's Way of Establishing the Nation, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - The Good Wine Last, (1853?) (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Grace Dispensed by a Law, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Grace Dispensed by Law, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - A Great Life Begins Early, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Heavenly State No. I, No. II, No. III, No. IV, 1842-1843, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - The Holy Spirit (incomplete), ca. 1875 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Hosea 6:3, 1837 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Inspiration, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - John 14:2, 1843 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Long Suffering, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - The Largest Love, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Luke 10:20, 1842 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Meaning of the Supper, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - The Motions of Sin, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Natural Science and Moral Philosophy, 1832 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Nothing in God's Attributes to be Spared, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Our Unthanking Way Accounted For, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Personality Developed by Religion, 1854 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Power From On High, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - The Prayer of Expectation, ca. 1850 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - The Preparations of Eternity, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Psalm 125, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Psalm 126:5, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Pure Love, 1848 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Revelation, 1839 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - The Sin of Being Only Negative to God, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Souls Enobled by Nearness to God, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Spiritual Things the Only Solid, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Subdue Evil by Enduring Evil, 1848 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - There is a Moral Governor, 1832 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Unconscious Prophecy, 1854 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - What is Faith?, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - The Word Grace Revived, 1869 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Fragments, 1848-1857, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Published sermons and discourses
    - Address before the Hartford Co. Agricultural Society, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Argument fo "Discourses on Christian Nurture", 1847 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Barbarism the First Danger, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - The Character of Jesus, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Commemorative Discourse delivered in North Church, Hartford, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Common Schools, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - The Day of Roads, 1846 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Discourse on the Slavery Question, 1839 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - The Fathers of New England, 1849 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Moral Tendencies and Results of Human History, 1843 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - The Moral Uses of Great Pestilences, 1849 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - The Moral Uses of the Sea, 1845 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - The Northern Iron, 1854 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Oration delivered before the Society of Phi Beta Kappa, 1848 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Parting Words, 1859 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Politics Under the Law of God, 1844 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Popular Government by Divine Right, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Position and Power (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Prosperity Our Duty, 1847 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Religious Music, 1852 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Reverses Needed, 1861 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Society and Religion: A Sermon for California, 1856 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Speech for Connecticut, 1851 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Spiritual Dislodgements, 1857 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous writings
    - The Faith-Talent Wanting Education for the Pulpit, 1873 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Letter to The Independent, 1856 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Need of Regeneration (sermon extract), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Patent No. 1177 (Heating stove), 1839 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Patent No. 6238 (Air-heating furnace), 1849 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Prayer for a wedding, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - The Religious Situation in New England (Box 5, Folder 32)
- Material Written about Bushnell, 1843; Series IV
  - Letter Written to Dr. Bushnell, of Hartford, on the Certain Passages of his Address..., 1843 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Printed letter from B. Tyler to Bushnell, 1847 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - What Does Dr. Bushnell Mean?, 1847 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Contribution of CC., now declared in full as Criticus Critorium, 1849 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Remonstrance and Complaint of the Association of Fairfield West to the Hartford Central Assn., 1850 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Appeal of the Association of Fairfield West to the Associated Ministers of the General Assn. Of CT, 1852 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - The Doctrines Held by Dr. Bushnell, 1872 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Address by Dr. T.T. Munger, 1902 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Bushnell Centenary - 193rd Annual Meeting of General Assn. of CT, 1902 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Newspaper clippings from: The Hartford Courant and The Hartford Weekly Times, 1902 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 37)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series V
  - Biographical and genealogical material
    - Letter from A. Cheseborough to Dr. Munger, 1902 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Notes, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Certificate of church standing signed by Bushnell, 1849 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Illustration of Bushnell, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 39)